Our home is burning.
我が家が燃えている
Rapid climate change is destabilizing our world.
急速な気候変動が世界を脅かしている
It seems our emissions will not fall quickly enough to avoid runaway warming
排出の削減は温暖化の抑止には不十分そうで
and we may soon hit tipping points that will lead to the collapse of ecosystems
生態系が崩壊する臨界点も近そうだし
and our civilization.
人類の文明も危うい
While scientists, activists and much of the younger generation urge action,
科学者、活動家、多数の若者が
行動を促すものの
it appears most politicians are not committed to do anything meaningful
ほとんどの政治家は
意味ある活動に取り組まず
while the fossil fuel industry still works actively against change.
化石燃料産業は依然として
変化を強く拒んでいる
It seems humanity can't overcome its greed and obsession with short term profit and personal gain
人類は短期的・個人的な利益への欲望と執着を
克服できない
to save itself.
保身のためだ
And so for many the future looks grim and hopeless.
多くの人には
未来は厳しく絶望的にみえる
Young people feel particularly anxious and depressed.
特に若者は不安で憂鬱だ
Instead of looking ahead to a lifetime of opportunity they wonder if they will even have a future
想像するのは未来のチャンスではなく
「未来があるのか」や
or if they should bring kids into this world.
「こんな世界に子供を産むべきか」だ
It's an age of doom and hopelessness and giving up seems the only sensible thing to do.
今は破滅と絶望の時代であり
諦めることだけが賢明な行動に見える
But that's not true.
だが、それは真実ではない
You are not doomed. Humanity is not doomed.
あなたの破滅も
人類の破滅も確定していないのだ
Despite the seriousness of the situation, for years positive trends have accumulated
深刻な状況の一方
ポジティブな動向も長期的に蓄積されており
and there is finally some good news and a clear path towards our collective climate goals.
気候の共通目標への好材料と
明確な道筋がついに整ってきた
Welcome to our Ted talk, please watch this video to the end
Tedトークへようこそ
最後まで視聴してください
– check out our detailed sources afterwards to learn more.
詳細は概要欄の情報源リンクから
Ok! Let’s start with the scariest things.
よし！まずは最も恐ろしい内容から
Canceling the Apocalypse
【終末を拒否する】
Some of the most widely shared stories about Climate Change are that it is an existential threat
気候変動を人類存亡の危機とする捉え方が
広く共有されている
– the end of human civilization and maybe even our own extinction event.
文明の終焉、そして人類の絶滅まであると
And that it is basically unavoidable now. But what does science actually say?
もはや終末は不可避とされるが
科学者の見解はどうだろう？
As of 2022 the global average temperature has risen 1.2 degrees celsius compared to preindustrial times.
2022年現在、世界の平均気温は
産業革命以前に比べて1.2℃上昇している
Limiting warming to 1.5 degrees was the most ambitious goal of the Paris agreement
1.5℃までに抑えるのが
パリ協定での最大目標だったが
but we are not likely to meet it.
実現できそうにない
Already with the warming we have today, hot places will get hotter,
すでに現時点の温暖化で
暑い地域はより暑く
wet places wetter and the risk and strength of extreme weather events increase significantly.
湿潤な地域はより湿潤となり
異常気象のリスクと程度は有意に増加している
Warming beyond 2 degrees makes all of these extremes more extreme,
2℃を超える温暖化は
現状をさらに悪化させる
extreme weather events more common with more ecosystems under major pressure.
異常気象はより一般的になり
生態系への圧力も強まって
Some will not survive.
存続できない種も出る
At 3 degrees significant parts of earth, especially in developing countries,
3℃上昇するとかなりの地域
特に途上国で
might become unable to feed their populations.
人口を養えなくなるかも
Heat waves will become a major global issue.
熱波が世界の重要課題となり
Large scale natural systems will break down.
自然界の仕組みの大枠が破壊される
The scale and frequency of hurricanes, fires and droughts will further increase
ハリケーン、山火事、干ばつの
規模と頻度がさらに増加し
and cause trillions in damage.
膨大な被害を招く
Poor regions and subsistence farmers will be hit the hardest.
貧しい地域や自給自足の農家は特に深刻で
Hundreds of millions of people will need to leave their homes.
何億人もが移住を迫られるだろう
In the 4-8 degree range the apocalypse begins
4-8℃の上昇で終末が始まる
– the hothouse earth, where things change so quickly,
温室状態の地球は
物事の変化が激しく
that it may become unable to support our large human population and billions may perish,
人口を養いきれなくなって
数十億人が滅び
leaving the rest on a hostile alien planet.
残りは見知らぬ過酷な惑星に残されるかも
A decade ago, for lack of action and perspective,
10年前、行動と展望の欠如から
many scientists assumed a 4+ degree world was our future
多くの科学者は
4℃以上増加する未来を想定し
and a lot of public communication focused on exactly this future path.
多くの広報は
まさにこの未来に焦点をあてていた
Luckily, it's much less likely that this version of the apocalypse will come to pass.
幸運にも
このような終末の可能性は低くなっている
If current climate policies stagnate,
現在の気候政策が停滞すると
we're likely to end up with warming 3 degrees celsius by 2100.
2100年までに3℃の温暖化で終わりそうだ
Which is scary and tragic and far from acceptable.
これは恐ろしく、悲劇的で
受け入れられないが
But this is actually good news – how?
いいニュースでもある
―なぜか？
In the last decade, we have seen enough progress that most scientists now think that we have likely avoided apocalyptic climate change.
この10年で、多くの科学者が
終末的な気候変動は回避されたという立場になった
Although substantial risk still remains,
まだ大きなリスクは残るが
we can pretty confidently say that humanity isn't going anywhere.
人類は滅亡しないと自信を持って言える
Civilization might have to change, but it will endure.
文明は変化を強いられるが
滅びはしない
Which begs the question: What has changed over the last ten years and is this really good news?
ここで疑問が生じる
この10年での変化とは？それは本当に吉報なのか？
The Invisible Shift
【見えない変化】
You probably know this story:
次の内容はご存じかもしれない
The last decade has been an immense failure for climate policies around the world.
「過去10年、世界の気候政策は大失敗だった」
Instead of passing comprehensive, binding bills that would meaningfully reduce emissions
「排出削減に効果的で拘束力のある法案を通さず」
we mostly did: nothing.
「ほぼ何もしないことを選んだ」
A lost decade with one negative record after another.
「相次ぐネガティブ記録の
失われた10年だった」
And this story is true and it is one reason why so many people are giving up.
この内容は正しいし
多くにとって諦める根拠だ
But it is not the whole picture.
だが、これが全てではない
Despite the lack of climate policies and ongoing lobbying and misinformation campaigns from the fossil fuel industries,
気候政策の欠如や
化石燃料産業によるロビー活動と情報攪乱の一方
there was a lot of progress.
多くの進展もあったのだ
Let us go back 20 years to see why today is so different:
現状の変化を見るため
20年前に戻ろう
Between 2000 and 2010,
2000年-2010年
greenhouse gas emissions had grown by 24%,
温室効果ガスの排出量は24％増加し
three times as much as the increase in the previous decade.
過去10年の増加量の3倍だった
Subsidies for fossil fuels aimed at promoting economic growth,
経済成長のための
化石燃料への補助金が
caused a colossal increase in their consumption.
消費量を激増させたのだ
For emerging countries like China and India coal was the cheapest fuel for growth
中国やインド等の新興国には
石炭は最も安価な燃料で
while rich countries showed little interest in changing their ways.
豊かな国々も変わろうとしなかった
In 2010, many people expected these trends to continue.
2010年、この傾向が続くと多数が思った
Instead of decreasing fossil fuel use its consumption would rise.
化石燃料の利用は低下でなく増加するのだと
The next decade turned out to be very different though.
だが次の10年は全く違った
First of all, coal burning in emerging countries like India
has been slowed down or leveled off, like in China.
まず、インドなど新興国での石炭利用は
中国のように安定または低下しており
And it has plummeted in rich countries like the UK and US.
英米のような富裕国では急落している
Since 2015 three-quarters of planned coal plants have been canceled
and 44 countries have committed to stop building them.
2015年以降、石炭発電所の計画の3/4が中止となり
44ヵ国が新設を見送った
Ten years ago that would have seemed like wishful thinking,
10年前なら楽観論だが
but today we can say with confidence: Coal is dying.
今は断言できる：石炭は死につつある
It is just not competitive anymore.
もはや競争力がない
Because technologies we thought would remain expensive
当面は高価だろうという技術が
matured rapidly instead.
急速に成熟したからだ
Renewable electricity has shown explosive progress.
再生可能エネルギーは爆発的に進歩した
In a mere decade wind energy got three times cheaper.
たった10年で風力発電は3倍安く
Solar electricity is now ten times cheaper!
太陽光は10倍安くなっている
Cheaper than coal or any other fossil-fuel burning power plant,
これは石炭や他の化石燃料の発電より安い
despite the massive subsidies and global infrastructure propping up fossil fuels.
化石燃料には世界的なインフラと
巨額の補助金があるのにだ
25 times more solar and nearly 5 times more wind electricity is produced today compared with ten years ago,
10年前と比べ、太陽光発電は25倍
風力発電は5倍近く行われているが
which is of course not nearly enough.
もちろん全く十分でない
One of the biggest obstacles is the variability of their power output.
最大の障害の一つは
その出力のバラつきだ
Renewables need a lot of energy storage to be a reliable power source,
like expensive batteries.
再生可能エネルギーの信頼獲得には
高級バッテリーのような貯蔵先が多数必要だ
Amazingly battery prices have decreased by 97% in the past 30 years,
驚くべきことに
バッテリーの価格低下は過去30年で97％
60% in the last decade alone
10年だけでも60％で
– which will serve all kinds of green technology like electric cars.
電気自動車など
全てのグリーンテクノロジーに有用だ
You might say, well that's great but didn't Kurzgesagt's last climate video
素晴らしいことだが
Kurzgesagtの前回の気候動画の主張は
say that while wind and solar are nice, we need nothing less than a fundamental transition of our global industrial system?
「風力や太陽光は重要だが
産業システムの根本的な転換が最重要」では？
Yes but luckily the shift goes beyond just the energy sector.
その通りだが
幸運にも躍進はエネルギー部門だけではない
Throughout the economy people are working on improving current technology to lower emissions.
経済全体で
人々は排出削減への技術改善に取り組んだ
We're rapidly replacing old incandescent light bulbs
with LEDs that are ten times more efficient.
古い白熱電球を、効率10倍のLEDへと
急速に置き換えている
In 2020 about 7 out of 10 new cars in Norway were electric or hybrid
2020年、新車の10台中7台が
電気自動車かハイブリッド車だった
– In 2021 it was already 8 out of 10.
2021年には10台中8台だ
And the list goes on, from electric heating and better insulation to ships traveling at half speed to save fuel.
改善リストは、電気暖房や断熱材の改善から
速度を半分にして燃料を節約する船まで続く
Wherever you look you find scientists, engineers and entrepreneurs
どこにでも科学者、技術者、起業家がいて
trying to solve some aspect of climate change.
気候変動の関係に取り組んでいる
Enormous amounts of human ingenuity are being brought to bear on this problem
急速な気候変動の抑制を
人々が重視するほどに
with more and more people deciding to prioritize preventing rapid climate change.
人類の膨大な創意工夫が
問題解決に活用される
Solutions for low-carbon production of cement, electronics and steel,
セメント、電子機器、鉄鋼の
低炭素での生産方法や
and innovations like artificial meat and carbon capture are in the works.
人工肉や炭素回収等の技術革新が進行中だ
The more of these technologies we deploy; the cheaper new and better technology gets.
これら技術を導入するほど
優れた新技術の価格が下がる
The cheaper they get, the more people use them. And so on.
安価なら需要も増え、という具合だ
We can see the impact already:
影響は確認済みで
The domestic CO2 output of rich countries is falling without a major recession.
大きな不況もなく
富裕国のCO2排出量は減少している
Since the 2000, the EU as a whole shows a 21% decrease,
2000年以降、EU全体では21％
Italy 28%, the UK 35%, Denmark 43%.
イタリアで28％、イギリスで35％
デンマークで43％も減少している
But the best news may be that emissions are no longer necessarily coupled with economic growth.
更に良い知らせは排出が
成長と連動しなくなったことにある
In the past this was an inconvenient truth
かつて、豊かになるためには
– to get richer, you had to emit more.
排出量を増やす必要があった
Which led to fierce arguments between developing and developed countries about the fairness of reducing emissions
そのため国の間で激論が交わされた
排出量低減は貧困の維持を意味し
while their populations were still poor.
公平性に問題があったが
But in the last decade we have seen that it IS possible to increase prosperity without increasing emissions.
この10年で経済成長は
排出を増やさなくても可能だとわかった
missions in the Czech Republic dropped 13% while their GDP grew by 27%!
チェコ共和国は排出量を13％低減したにもかかわらず
GDPは27％成長した
France reduced their CO2 emissions by 14% while increasing GDP by 15%!
フランスは排出量を14％低減した一方
GDPは15％増加し
Romania saw an 8% decrease and 35% growth!
ルーマニアも8％減少し、35％成長した
And even the largest economy on earth - the USA
そして最大の経済大国アメリカでさえ
- decreased emissions by 4% while growing their GDP by 26%!
排出量は4％減少した一方GDPは26％成長している
Some of you may call this a numbers trick.
これらを数字上のトリックと言う者もいるだろう
That rich countries are just exporting emissions to poorer nations
豊かな国は製造業などの排出量の多い汚れ仕事を
by moving the dirty parts of their economies like manufacturing.
貧しい国に押し付けているに過ぎないと
But even when we account for all of our imported goods,
しかしたとえすべての輸入品を考慮に入れたとしても
the numbers still look positive!
この数字は依然プラスとなる
It's no longer a matter of having to choose between prosperity and the climate
もはや一昔前の、繁栄と気候のどちらを取るか
as it seemed to be a decade ago.
というような問題ではないのだ
Developing countries will profit from that
途上国は後追いのおかげで
because as rich countries pay for the expensive development of green technologies,
富裕国が開発費用を負担した技術を
they can adopt them more cheaply.
格安で導入できる
They can skip most of the high emission phase that today's rich countries went through.
彼らは最も排出量の高かった工程をスキップできるのだ
We are at the point where not decarbonizing is a bad business decision.
我々は脱炭素しないという決定が
非合理であるという地点にいる
And we haven't even really talked about solutions like carbon capture.
炭素回収のような解決策については
まだ十分に議論されていない
In 2000 it didn't really exist.
2000年時点では存在すらしていなかったが
In 2022 that technology does exist
2022年現在、これらの技術は存在し
and costs around $600 to remove one ton of CO2 from the atmosphere.
1トンCO2を除去するのに600ドルかかっている
As investment pours in and the technology matures and begins to scale,
投資が行われ技術が成熟して
規模が拡大すると
it is likely that these costs will plummet over the next few decades.
コストは今後急落すると思われる
So everything's fine then?
つまり、何も問題はないのだろうか？
Well let us not get carried away here
まあ、そうは問屋が卸さない
- all of these processes are great but not nearly fast enough.
これらの技術は素晴らしいが速度が足りない
We are still doing way too little and technology will not magically solve everything.
我々の行動はまだ少なく
技術も魔法のようにはいかない
We need to use fewer resources and use them longer,
我々は資源を節約し長く使い
design consumer goods that are repairable and durable and decrease our energy requirements.
修理可能で長持ちする製品を作り
使用エネルギーを削減する必要がある
We need much better infrastructure, agriculture and cities.
またインフラ、農業、街づくりを
改善する必要がある
It will still be hard work, especially to get the right policies passed and enacted.
特に適切な政策を成立させるのは
相変わらず難題だが
But for the first time ever, there are a few trendlines pointing solidly in the right direction.
いつくかの傾向は
正しい方向を示し始めたのだ
And now imagine – If all of this was achieved without proper financial and political support
想像したい
もしこれらが適切な財政及び政治的支援なく
and despite fossil fuel lobbying
化石燃料のロビー活動にも関わらず達成されたとしたら
– just think what humanity can do when climate change finally gets the political attention and funding it needs.
考えてほしい、気候変動が政治的注目と
資金を得たとき人類に何ができるかを
So is it ok to feel hopeful again?
うん、やっぱり希望が見えてきそう？
The situation is still dire and serious,
状況はいまだ深刻だ
so what is the point of focusing on this side of the story?
じゃあ、この側面に注目する理由は？
The Trap of Hopelessness
【絶望という罠】
Climate change can feel overwhelming and make your future seem bleak.
気候変動に圧倒され
未来は暗いと思うことがある
The sadness and hopelessness that many people feel is real and very destructive because it causes apathy.
悲しみや絶望感は現実であり
破壊を見過ごす無関心へと繋がりがちだ
Apathy that is only serving the fossil fuel industry
無関心とは化石燃料産業を救うものであり
that is still delaying change however it can.
彼らはできる限り変化を遅らせようとしている
In a sense they have weaponized hopelessness.
ある意味、彼らは絶望を武器としているのだ
We are now in phase 4 in the public debate about rapid climate change action:
我々は急速な気候変動に対して第4段階目にいる
Phase 1 was: Climate Change is not real.
第1段階は
「気候変動は事実ではない」
Phase 2 was: Climate Change is real but not caused by humans.
第2段階は「気候変動は事実だ
しかし人類が原因ではない」
Phase 3 was: Climate Change may be caused by humans but it's not that bad.
第3段階は「気候変動は人類が原因だ
しかしさほど悪いことではない」
Phase 4 is: Climate Change is no longer avoidable.
第4段階は
「気候変動は避けられない」
We are doomed and it doesn't matter what we do.
「人類がなにをしようともう手遅れだ」
If we want the world to change, we first need to believe that change is possible.
もし世界を変えたいと望むなら
まず変化が可能だと信じる必要があり
And we have an abundance of evidence that it is.
実際それが可能であると示す証拠も持っている
Changes to our industrial system are gaining momentum,
変化に対し、産業は勢いを増し
technology gets better and cheaper, climate change has become a key issue in most free elections.
技術は安く高度になり
気候変動は多くの自由選挙で重要な争点となってきた
As more and more younger people move into influential positions,
多くの若者達が影響力をもつにつれ
they prioritize climate change and work on new solutions.
気候変動は優先され
新しい解決策への取り組みも増えている
In 2022 most governments not only acknowledge it
2022年では多くの政府が
but set their own net zero goals – in democratic and autocratic countries.
ネットゼロを目標としている
民主的あるいは専制的政治体系にかかわらずだ
The results of years of fighting a steep uphill battle are now clearly visible.
険しい道程を長年戦い続けてきた成果が
今はっきりと現れているのだ
The pressure needs to keep increasing, to make sure that the promises made today are actually kept!
今日の約束が本当に守られるよう
圧力をかけ続ける必要がある
Climate doomerism is the equivalent of giving up even though you can still prevent not just the worst case
気候破滅主義は諦めることに等しい
まだ我々が最悪のケースを防げるばかりか
but also mitigate most of the bad things, make changes in time to adapt better
多くの悪影響を和らげ
変化を間に合わせ
and prevent the poorest from suffering.
まだ貧困層の苦痛すら防げるのに
That is why hopelessness and apathy are so dangerous.
これこそ絶望と無関心が危険な理由だ
If the last, in many ways wasted decade, has shown anything,
もしこの10年間が無駄だったと感じられたとしても
then it's that progress is being made
それは進歩があったということであり
and that dire scenarios are just predictions – not our sealed fate.
悲惨なシナリオは単なる予想であって
未来が確定したわけではないのだ
As of 2022, based on current global policies, we will end up in a 3 degrees world.
2022年現在、世界的な政策に基づくと
我々は3℃の世界に行き着くが
Now it is our job to yet again prove the predictions wrong
この予想も誤りだったと証明する必要がある
– despite how serious and urgent things are.
いかに事態が深刻で緊急であったとしても
To turn that 3 degrees into a 2 degrees and then see where we can go from there.
3℃を2℃にし、さらに
未来を希求する必要がある
For that we need hope.
そのためにも、希望が必要だ
And we hope we gave you that today, at least a little.
そして今回、我々が少しでも
それを視聴者に与えられたらと願う
That you feel that things are serious but also that you have a future.
事態は深刻だが
未来もあるのだと感じてもらえたなら
That you can have kids without dooming them or the world.
子供を持つことができ
その未来も世界も破滅する宿命にないのだと
That taking action today is worth it.
今、行動を起こすことはそれだけの価値がある
And that despite powerful industries doing everything to delay it, society is changing.
強力な産業界がいかなる遅滞工作に勤しもうと
社会は変わりつつある
If you need a more concrete roadmap of what you can do personally
もし自分に何ができるのか
具体的なロードマップを知りたければ
– we are working on a follow up video to talk about that in greater detail.
現在詳細なビデオを制作中なので期待してほしい
Doomerism, inactivity and weaponized hopelessness
破滅主義、無関心と絶望こそが
are the only trump cards left for the powers that don't want change.
変化を望まない者たちの切り札だ
Don't let them win.
奴らを勝たせてはならない
We are still excited about the future.
我々は未来にワクワクしています
And we think one of the best things you can do to keep your optimism and curiosity up
そして楽観と好奇心を持ち続けるための方法の一つは
is to learn new things.
新しいことを学ぶことです
If you don't know where to start, our friends from Brilliant.org have got you covered.
何から始めればいいのかわかない人は
Brilliant.orgにお任せください
Brilliant makes math and science accessible and fun with a hands-on approach.
Brilliantは数学や科学を
楽しく身近に学ぶことができます
More than 60 interactive courses like
60以上の対話的な
„The joy of problem solving“ or „Scientific thinking“
「問題解決の喜び」や「科学的思考」
といったコースが
give you the tools to crack problems in math, science and computer science
あなたに数学や科学の問題に
対処するための道具を与えてくれ
that are all designed to get your intuition going and give you plenty of aha-experience.
これらは全て直感を刺激しあっと驚く
体験ができるよう設計されています
Lessons will surprise you with storytelling, code-writing tasks and interactive challenges
レッスンはあなたを驚かせるストーリーや
対話的なチャレンジなど
– basically using whatever keeps you interested and entertained.
興味や楽しさを与えられる方法に満ちています
All the content is interactive: instead of just reading and listening to explanations,
全てのコンテンツは対話的であり
単に読んだり聞いたりするだけではなく
you drag and drop, manipulate shapes and diagrams, make selections and answer questions.
ドラッグ＆ドロップしたり、図形を操作したり
質問に答えたり
This way you learn something almost without you noticing it.
気づかないうちに何かを学んでいるかも
And tiny step by step you'll build up your long-term understanding of science and get closer to your STEM goals.
小さな積み重ねが科学への理解を深め
STEM教育の目標に近づくことでしょう
To start looking at the world of science from a different perspective,
科学の世界を別の視点から見るためには
go to brilliant.org/nutshell and sign up for free.
brilliant.org/nutshell にアクセスしてください
登録は無料です
And there's an extra perk for kurzgesagt viewers:
さらに Kurzgesagt 視聴者には特別特典
the first 200 people to use the link get 20% off their annual membership,
先着200名まで20%オフの年間メンバーシップにご招待
which unlocks all of Brilliant's courses in math, science, and computer science.
数学、科学、コンピューターなど全てのコースに
ご利用いただけます
At kurzgesagt we love to create things that seem impossible at first
Kurzgesagt は一見不可能と思えるものを
形にすることが大好きです
– Brilliant can help you acquire the skills to do that.
Brilliant はその手伝いをしてくれるでしょう
Continue your quest for knowledge with Kurzgesagt
- Kurzgesagt と知識の冒険へ出かけよう -
Explore your creativity
- 創造性を探究し -
Discover the world around you
- 身の回りの奇跡を発見し -
Travel with your friends
- 友と旅立とう -